DAVID GOEDICKE

d.goedicke@cornell.edu http://davidgoedicke.com

I specialize in immersive experiences, human-robot interactions, and virtual environments. My work is rooted in enabling qualitative behavioral methods and Wizard of Oz'ed prototypes through VR/XR simulators to assess designs before implementation. These methods facilitate complex interactions among users, robots, and simulated agents in virtual and augmented spaces. Drawing on a diverse background in interactive art, game development, and music, I enrich the qualitative depth of these technologies. My research is geared towards advancing our understanding of human-technology interactions, with implications, particularly designing behaviors for robots and automated systems. As an educator, my pedagogical approach promotes project-based, hands-on learning to empower students to navigate and solve complex problems independently.

EDUCATION

2018–2023 Cornell Tech | New York City, NY

Ph.D. in Information Science

Dissertation: DRIVING SIMULATION FOR INTERACTION

Committee: Wendy Ju, Malte Jung, Serge Belongie

2014–2017 University of Twente | Enschede, Netherlands

M.Sc. in Human Media Interaction

2010–2014 University of Twente | Enschede, Netherlands

B.Sc. Creative Technology Graduate with Cum Laude

EMPLOYMENT

2023-NOW Post Doctoral Researcher

Future Automation Research Lab (Wendy Ju)

Cornell Tech

2020 Research and Development Intern

Toyota Research Institute - Internship

ADVISOR: Yasuda Hiroshi

2019 Research and Development Intern

Samsung Electronics · Internship ADVISOR: Gregory Dudek

2017 Visiting Research Scholar

Stanford University - Center for Design Research

ADVISOR: Wendy Ju

2016 Visiting Research Scholar

Nissan Research-SV

ADVISOR: Erik Vinkhuyzen, Melissa Cefkin

2014-2016 Research assistant

Human Media Interaction group

ADVISOR: Dennis Reidsma, Robby van Delden

PUBLICATIONS

JOURNAL ARTICLES

David Goedicke, Carmel Zolkov, Natalie Friedman, Talia Wise, Avi Parush, Wendy Ju. "Strangers in a Strange Land: New Experimental System for Understanding Driving Culture Using VR". In: *IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology* 71.4 (Apr. 2022), pp. 3399–3413. ISSN: 1939-9359. DOI: 10.1109/TVT.2022.3152611.

CONFERENCE PAPERS (REFEREED)

Fanjun Bu, Stacey Li, **David Goedicke**, Mark Colley, Gyanendra Sharma, Wendy Ju. "Portobello: Extending Driving Simulation from the Lab to the Road". In: *Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. CHI '24. Hawai: Association for Computing Machinery, 2024. DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642341. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3613904.3642341.

Nialah Jenae Wilson-Small, **David Goedicke**, Kirstin Petersen, Shiri Azenkot. "A Drone Teacher: Designing Physical Human-Drone Interactions for Movement Instruction". In: *Proceedings of the 2023 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction*. HRI '23. Stockholm, Sweden: Association for Computing Machinery, 2023, pp. 311–320. ISBN: 9781450399647. DOI: 10.1145/3568162.3576985. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3568162.3576985.

David Goedicke, Alexandra W.D. Bremers, Sam Lee, Fanjun Bu, Hiroshi Yasuda, Wendy Ju. "XR-OOM: MiXed Reality Driving Simulation with Real Cars for Research and Design". In: *Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. CHI '22. New Orleans, LA, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, 2022. ISBN: 9781450391573. DOI: 10.1145/3491102.3517704. URL:

https://doi.org/10.1145/3491102.3517704.

Andrea Cuadra, **David Goedicke**, J.D. Zamfirescu-Pereira. "Democratizing Design and Fabrication Using Speech: Exploring Co-Design with a Voice Assistant". In: *Proceedings of the 3rd Conference on Conversational User Interfaces*. CUI '21. Bilbao (online), Spain: Association for Computing Machinery, 2021. ISBN: 9781450389983. DOI: 10.1145/3469595.3469624. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3469595.3469624.

J.D. Zamfirescu-Pereira, David Sirkin, **David Goedicke**, Ray LC, Natalie Friedman, Ilan Mandel, Nikolas Martelaro, Wendy Ju. "Fake It to Make It: Exploratory Prototyping in HRI". In: *Companion of the 2021 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction*. HRI '21 Companion. Boulder, CO, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, 2021, pp. 19–28. 18 B N: 9781450382908. DOI: 10.1145/3434074.3446909. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3434074.3446909.

Jamy Li, Rebecca Currano, David Sirkin, **David Goedicke**, Hamish Tennent, Aaron Levine, Vanessa Evers, Wendy Ju. "On-Road and Online Studies to Investigate Beliefs and Behaviors of Netherlands, US and Mexico Pedestrians Encountering Hidden-Driver Vehicles". In: *Proceedings of the 2020 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction*. HRI '20. Cambridge, United Kingdom: Association for Computing Machinery, 2020, pp. 141–149. ISBN: 9781450367462. DOI: 10.1145/3319502.3374790. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3319502.3374790.

Marcel Walch, Stacey Li, Ilan Mandel, **David Goedicke**, Natalie Friedman, Wendy Ju. "Crosswalk Cooperation: A Phone-Integrated Driver-Vehicle Cooperation Approach to Predict the Crossing Intentions of Pedestrians in Automated Driving". In: 12th International Conference on Automotive User Interfaces and Interactive Vehicular Applications. AutomotiveUI '20. Virtual Event, DC, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, 2020, pp. 74–77. ISBN: 9781450380669. DOI: 10.1145/3409251.3411727. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3409251.3411727.

Vincent Zhang, Natalie Friedman, **David Goedicke**, Dmitriy Rivkin, Michael Jenkin, Xue Liu, Gregory Dudek. "The Answer Is Blowing in the Wind: Directed Air Flow for Socially-acceptable Human-Robot Interaction." In: *Proceedings International Conference on Robotics, Computer Vision, and Intelligent Systems (ROBOVIS)*. 2020.

Sven Krome, **David Goedicke**, Thomas J. Matarazzo, Zimeng Zhu, Zhenwei Zhang, J. D. Zamfirescu-Pereira, Wendy Ju. "How People Experience Autonomous Intersections: Taking a First-Person Perspective". In: *Proceedings of the 11th International Conference on Automotive User Interfaces and Interactive Vehicular Applications*. AutomotiveUI '19. Utrecht, Netherlands: Association for Computing

Machinery, 2019, pp. 275–283. ISBN: 9781450368841. DOI: 10.1145/3342197.3344520. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3342197.3344520.

David Goedicke, Jamy Li, Vanessa Evers, Wendy Ju. "VR-OOM: Virtual Reality On-ROad Driving SiMulation". In: *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. CHI '18. Montreal QC, Canada: Association for Computing Machinery, 2018, pp. 1–11. ISBN: 9781450356206. DOI: 10.1145/3173574.3173739. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3173574.3173739.

WORKSHOPS PAPERS (REFEREED)

Karoline Brehm, Yan Shvartzshnaider, **David Goedicke**. *Contextual Integrity of A Virtual (Reality) Classroom*. 2023. arXiv: 2303.13684 [cs.CY].

Madiha Zahrah Choksi, **David Goedicke**. Whose Text Is It Anyway? Exploring BigCode, Intellectual Property, and Ethics. 2023. arXiv: 2304.02839 [cs.CY].

DEMOS, VIDEOS, AND WORK-IN-PROGRESS (REFEREED)

Natalie Friedman, **David Goedicke**, Vincent Zhang, Dmitriy Rivkin, Michael Jenkin, Ziedune Degutyte, Arlene Astell, Xue Liu, Gregory Dudek. "Capturing attention with wind". In: *Proceedings Workshop on Integrating Multidisciplinary Approaches to Advanced Physical Human-Robot Interaction*. *Held alongside the IEEE 2020 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA).

Michael Jenkin, Natalie Friedman, **David Goedicke**, Vincent Zhang, Dmitriy Rivkin, Ziedune Degutyte, Arlene Astell, Xue Liu, Gregory Dudek. "Out of my way! Exploring Different Modalities for Robots to Ask People to Move Out of the Way". In: *Proceedings Workshop on Active Vision and Perception in Human (Robot) Collaboration*. *Held alongside the 29th IEEE International Conference on Robot and Human Interactive Communication. September. 2020.

David Goedicke, Harald Haraldsson, Navit Klein, Lunshi Zhou, Avi Parush, Wendy Ju. "ReRun: Enabling Multi-Perspective Analysis of Driving Interaction in VR". In: *Companion of the 2023 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction*. HRI '23. Stockholm, Sweden: Association for Computing Machinery, 2023, pp. 889–890. ISBN: 9781450399708. DOI: 10.1145/3568294.3580211. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3568294.3580211.

Regina Bernhaupt, Mark Colley, **David Goedicke**, Alexander Meschtscherjakov, Bastian Pfleging, Andreas Riener, Shadan Sadeghian. "A Critical Perspective on Radically Innovating Personal Mobility". In: *Adjunct Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Automotive User Interfaces and Interactive Vehicular*

Applications. AutomotiveUI '22. Seoul, Republic of Korea: Association for Computing Machinery, 2022, pp. 215–218. ISBN: 9781450394284. DOI: 10.1145/3544999.3551689. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3544999.3551689.

ORGANIZED WORKSHOPS

David Goedicke, Wendy Ju. "Neural Nets for Music". In: Stanford University Stanford, CA 94305-8180 USA: Center for Computer Research in Music and Acoustics, 2019 & 2020. URL:

https://ccrma.stanford.edu/workshops/canceled-using-neural-nets-sonic-interaction-design.

David Goedicke, Hamish Tennent, Dylan Moore, Wendy Ju. "Acoustically Aware Robots: Detecting and Evaluating Sounds Robots Make and Hear". In: *Companion of the 2021 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction*. HRI '21 Companion. Boulder, CO, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, 2021, pp. 697–699. ISBN: 9781450382908. DOI: 10.1145/3434074.3444876. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3434074.3444876.

Nikolas Martelaro, J.D. Zamfirescu-Pereria, **David Goedicke**, David Sirkin, Wendy Ju. "Make This! Introduction to Electronics Prototyping Using Arduino". In: *Extended Abstracts of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. CHI EA '20. Honolulu, HI, USA: Association for Computing Machinery, 2020, pp. 1–4. ISBN: 9781450368193. DOI: 10.1145/3334480.3375052. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3334480.3375052.

Sven Krome, Eric Deng, **David Goedicke**, Wendy Ju, Ignacio Alverez, Jaka Sodnik, Andrew Veit, Francesco Grani. "Simulator Showdown: Pitch Your Virtual Ride". In: *Proceedings of the 11th International Conference on Automotive User Interfaces and Interactive Vehicular Applications: Adjunct Proceedings*. AutomotiveUI '19. Utrecht, Netherlands: Association for Computing Machinery, 2019, pp. 25–31. ISBN: 9781450369206. DOI: 10.1145/3349263.3350765. URL: https://doi.org/10.1145/3349263.3350765.

PREPRINT ARTICLES

Madiha Zahrah Choksi, Ilan Mandel, **David Goedicke**, Yan Shvartzshnaider. *Enclosed Loops: How open source communities become datasets*. 2023. arXiv: 2306.05598 [cs.CY].

David Goedicke, Mark Colley, Sebastian S. Feger, Michael Goedicke, Bastian Pfleging, Wendy Ju. *Towards Sustainable Research Data Management in Human-Computer Interaction*. 2023. arXiv: 2307.10467 [cs.HC].

Public Articles

Manaswi Saha, Wendy Ju, Mike Kuniavsky, **David Goedicke**. *Audio AR: An Introduction*. 2023. URL: https://medium.com/labs-notebook/audio-ar-an-introduction-698661405ff4.

RESEARCH GRANTS & GIFTS

FEDERAL GRANTS

National Science Foundation IIS-2212431: NSF-BSF: HCC: Medium: Cultural

Differences in Pedestrian-Autonomous Vehicle Interaction

Investigators: Wendy Ju (PI), Qian Yang, Cornell (Co-PI), Avi Parush, Technion

(Co-PI)

Amount: \$599,986

Dates: 9/01/2022 - 9/30/2024

National Science Foundation IIS-2107111: HCC: Medium: Cultural Differences in

Driving Interaction

Investigators: Wendy Ju (PI), Qian Yang, Cornell (Co-PI), Avi Parush, Technion

(Co-PI)

Amount: \$800,000

Dates: 10/01/2021 - 9/30/2024

HONORS & AWARDS

2012-2014 **B.Sc. Honors program** University of Twente.

SELECTED PRESS COVERAGE

2022 Cornell Chronicle Mixed-reality driving simulator a low-cost alternative

https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2022/04/mixed-reality-driving-simulator-low-

cost-alternative

2020 Cornell Chronicle 'Ghostdrivers' test cultural reactions to autonomous cars

https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2020/04/ghostdrivers-test-cultural-reactions-

autonomous-cars

TEACHING

Spring 2020 Masters Specialization Project

Master Student Projects at Cornell Tech with Prof. Estrin and Prof. Azenkot.

Fall 2019 Masters Specialization Project

Master Student Projects at Cornell Tech with Prof. Estrin and Prof. Azenkot.

Spring 2018 Developing and Designing Interactive Devices

Taught by Wendy Ju

2013-2016 University of Twente -Design Lab-, Teacher

Workshops on Augmented Reality and Virtual Reality in Unity.

Teaching and supervising B.S. Honors students in a Prototyping and Design Course

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Conference Organizing Committee Roles

2022 Social Media Chair

15th International ACM Conference on Automotive User Interfaces and Interactive Vehicular Applications (AutoUI)

2022 Video Chair

ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS)

REVIEWING SERVICE

ACM Conference in Human Factors in Computing (CHI) ACM/IEEE Human-Robot Interaction Conference (HRI) ACM Conference in Automotive User Interfaces (AutoUI) Spring Virtual Reality Journal